so this is Sangeeta Nika 3528 added to
suitor to fight this go so often
translator is the fire sermon
thus I heard one time the Blessed One
was running in Gaia and Gaius head with
1000 months they had the Blessed One
dress the monks monks all is on fire
what monks is the old that is on fire
the I monks is on fire forms are on fire
my consciousness is on fire my
impression is on fire also that which I
impression causes to appear felt
pleasant or painful of neither pleasure
nor nor neither painful nor pleasant
that also is on fire on fire with what
on fire with passion with anger on fire
with darkness with birth aging in depth
and so on so one thing like first thing
to note here it's things that are on
fire means fire is not in them so you
the I the forms and I consciousness the
fire takes them up takes them up through
passion through anger to down this it's
not that the fire is in the eye or in
the forms and the reason I say this it's
because often when people would say you
have a sight that induces I don't know
your will anger so it's it's on fire
with a virgin
hypothetically speaking you blame the
sight habitually you you sort of jump
into the conclusion into the assumption
that the aversion the anger is because
of the sight but it's not it's the anger
takes up the site which means that anger
or lust or or darkness that fire takes
that up as fuel but it's not it it's not
in it so what is then the fuel or rather
sorry we know where the fuel is but what
is the reason that the fire takes these
things up well the Buddha explains the
reason is on passion anger and darkness
delusion often translated I'll explain
later why we translated it down as here
so it's having passion
which means ah so passion is something
you are responsible for passion is not
in the sight in the beautiful sights a
version is not indeed in the ugly
disagreeable sights darkness it's not in
the neutral sites it's basically
something you choose to cultivate in
regard to those sites so it's the same
it's exactly the same principle that it
would have described for the five
aggregates and padana so the five
aggregates pancha pancha Conda and
Pancho Pinella Conda said Oberon is not
in the five aggregates so the assumption
is not in the five aggregates it's the
desire and lust in regard to the five
aggregates that assumption is there an
assumption literally means taking things
up for granted assuming them and that's
what what fire does takes them up so
it's not you don't do you you don't take
things up consciously in a sense of
sorry not you don't take things up
voluntarily or intentionally that's the
better world you take them up as a
result or rather taking up is the result
of you intentionally cultivating lust a
version cultivating passion aversion
darkness indolence a song that's how you
then that hard results that those things
become taken up that's how the fire sets
in and starts to burn so you can't just
say no to fire you can't just say no to
the assumptions you can't say no to
apirana that's why we choose to
translate this assumption on the world
open Anna we choose to translate this
assumption not as holding or attachment
because all of those things are
something you can be clearly conscious
or I'm holding on to this thus now I
will choose to let it go and it's not
intentional you cannot intentionally
choose to let to go because you're not
intentionally holding it so you're doing
something else intentionally did then
directly resulting in OPA Donna and
that's exactly like the fundamental
thing that you are responsible for that
is the determining dupa Donna in regard
to the five aggregates is
ignorance so choosing to ignore set the
nature of things that's it that's all
you need to do you just choose to turn a
blind eye on a certain characteristics
of your experience usually the
unpleasant ones automatically that
simultaneously resulting in determining
determining the presence of assumption
so you will assume things when you don't
know them so you don't know whether it's
the diesel so you assume it and again
you find assumptions there you don't
sort of intentionally create them or I
shall assume so and so now you just find
yourself assuming so-and-so because you
never question it you never looked at
you were always blind of the of the
nature of the thing even if you were
assuming it rightly the fact is you
don't know that and the reason you don't
know is because you never check that
assumption and that's exactly the nature
of Perdana the assumption in regard to
their form feeling perception intentions
and consciousness it's not this some
some great mystery of the aggregates
that you need to reveal and discover
it's simply ignoring certain fundamental
characteristics of the five aggregates
the assumption is they're so ignoring
the the certain characteristics of the
five aggregates or ignoring the the
nature of the senses means passion
aversion darkness in regard to them are
the attitude you choose to cultivate so
then they are on fire because of what
you do underneath so to speak so the
when you see a beautiful sight and you
have passion in regarded first you have
to stop blaming the beautiful sight for
the passion have to take responsibility
for the passion and the only way to do
that is to restrain acting out of that
passion habitually straight away towards
the site so once you restrained once you
feel the burning of the fire the burning
of the passion or aversion or even
delusion you get to realize okay so it's
it's underneath this fire is something
that I do which
results in me basically being liable to
burn when when the sights sounds melt a
starches create impressions on me and
that thing thats underneath is what the
Buddha described with certain subtle
attitudes of delighting in sight sound
smell stays touches welcoming sight
sound smell state touches adhering to
them hoping for so all these little
little attitudes that you cultivate
towards accepting the pleasant ones and
rejecting the unpleasant ones and you
just assume that it's fine to do so you
assume that you're in a position to do
so you assume that it's that is
absolutely normal to when there is
Pleasant you just go towards it and when
it's unpleasant you go away from it and
when it's neutral you just sort of be
blind of it'd be dull and and indolent
in regard to it and that assumption is
the direct cause then that these things
are on fire ignoring the nature of those
things because as the Buddha said so
Hajus how would you stop assuming that
it's fine to to adhere to these things
to reject these things
how would you stop delighting in sights
sounds smells tastes touches or having
being averse
how would you stop those attitudes so
you would stop them by seeing the danger
in doing so oh there is actually danger
in accepting the the beautiful sight in
the lighting in it in being on a
Leighton account of it so the danger is
not in the site the site is not
dangerous the eye is not dangerous even
the fire is not dangerous so to speak
the fire is just a symptom things that
are on fire means or they're burning
that's a symptom of that underlying fuel
so what is the danger of that fuel or
the danger is in in basically not seeing
that welcoming the lighting and hearing
being a legend around with that attitude
is dangerous
and why is it dangerous naturally you
would ask well because that which you
delighted is not in your control that
which you're welcoming hoping to last
hoping to come your way and persist and
stay and not leave you is not in your
control so can you delight inside sounds smells
so can you delight inside sounds smells
tastes touches without simultaneously
ignoring the fact that side sounds
smells tastes touches are not in your
control like literally inaccessible to you and
like literally inaccessible to you and
me like or not in my control but no they
are in excess they have life of their
own they don't even know about you so to
they don't even know about you so to
speak you don't exist for them so you
are doing picking these things up with
all this like emotional craving for
pleasure and so on so would you be able
to delight to welcome these things
without simultaneously ignoring that
they are not in your control so ignoring
that these things are not in your
control is a necessary basis for the
being able to delight rejoice belated
welcomed it adhere to it so then not
ignoring that these things are not in
your control means you will be unable to
delight in them doesn't mean you won't
see things with your eye
you won't recognize whether they're
beautiful agreeable or ugly and
disagreeable that all stays the same
it just means now you're not you're
being unable to ignore the nature the
context in which they appear such as
they're not in your control they give in
to it you are subjected to them you have
no say in their arising all these things
that again you can think about
theoretically and absolutely but that
that won't work in the same sense if you
think on that think of it on the level
of the actual currently enduring sites
sound smell taste are just thought the
mind so that's why that's what we
translate past as pressure and
impression because these things arise on
their own inner on the exercise pressure
on you automatically pressure like
pleasure exercises pressure to to go
towards it to have more
Robert pain exercises pressure to get
away from it it pressures you a neutral
feeling exercises pressure to it's
basically ignoring being doubt mentally
sort of unaware unmindful and so on
no not keeping that mental alertness
that's what neutral feeling pressures
you towards towards that darkness that's
a richness rate is down is because
delusion it's sort of again it has
certain connotations of this some
something you deluded about until you
figure it out you'll be deluded new it's
more of an attitude of the mind in the
same sense passion is an attitude
towards pleasure a version is an
attitude away from pain darkness is the
attitude towards that neutral feeling
that's kind of undistinguishable really
by by any means of pleasure or pain so
that's why recognition then the these
things are not in your control the dare
of the nature to cease having a reason
they're impermanent you you cannot you
cannot basically have them submit to
your will it's other way around will
then make you not delight in them
because if you know there is a beautiful
sight and if you know and it's any
second can be taken away any second it
can it can sort of intoxicate you and
and and completely make you spiral out
of control for example you would regard
that thing is dangerous you wouldn't go
near it so by regarding that by seeing
the danger in these things the Buddha
said you will stop delighting you will
stop welcoming it and by the way when
there is a version you do also delight
in your own attitude of trying to get
rid of that aversion you also accept
that attitude for granted so if you if
you see that the version has the reason
its own means
oh it's uncomfortable but I'm not saying
it having a reason if you have to see
it's just it's impossible for it to not
cease that's enough for you to not be
pressured by the diversion if you
maintain that context especially if you
clarify it further
so bye-bye seeing the danger in in the
in the eye and seeing the danger in the
forms and same goes for all the other
senses you will stop delighting in it
you will stop being a verse the words
that you will stop resisting it and you
will stop giving in to that mental
indolence and darkness bye-bye stop by
by stopping of those attitudes and those
choices you then remove that fuel for
the fire so the fire will diminish the
fire toward sight sound smell taste
touches so then you would see the same
sight they used to fill your mind with
passion or fill your mind with anger
that you'll be burning with now there is
no fire the site hasn't changed the I
haven't the ice has been change the
consciousness of that hasn't changed
you are still aware of the same things
what has changed now is there is no
necessary basis of your delighting in
those things thus there is no fire being
manifested because fire needs the
delight and to in order fire needs the
delight as in fire needs passion
aversion Adamas for it to burn it needs
to in need to fuel it so are the eyes on
fire so basically that attitude of fire
then takes send it whichever way you
look say on the experience of like a
disagreeable sight something fills you
you've seen something that fills you
with a version so it's it's the fire is
there because the aversion not because
of the eye not because of the sight not
because of you being aware of the eye on
the sides not even because of the
pressure that outside exhibits on you
the fire is there because of desire
because of passion because of a version
because of delusion because of darkness
whichever way you want to translate it
which is why then that fire takes up
anything within that relationship within
the domain of sight
so the eye will be on fire the sights
will be on fire everything in between
will be on fire so our consciousness
will be a fire pressure that that
experience exhibits on you impression
created by that site will be on fire
everything that's felt on account of
whatever you've seen Pleasant unpleasant
neither unpleasant or Pleasant that's
all on fire so what this states is that
through your unchecked delight welcoming
assuming not seeing the nature of the
sight sound smell taste touch is not
having reflected upon it sufficiently
enough you have accumulated the the
abundance of fire let's say like that
which now means that this fire is
rolling like once the big fire starts it
starts taking things up on its own so it
becomes kind of self-sufficient of
course for as long as that is I sight
sound smell taste touches as long as
there's things to be taking up by fire
fire will take it up so the only way to
diminish that fire it's not enough for
you to just not delight in these things
once twice three times thousand times
you have to develop the attitude of
Perpetual non delight of Perpetual non
resistance to pain non acceptance of
pleasure and not slipping into into
darkness on account of neutral feeling
and what what will constitute that
perpetual attitude well that depends on
the individual for somebody that might
be done in a shorter period of time for
somebody longer but on average you would
assume it will take quite a while
because it took quite a while to to
accumulate that the massive fire through
your unchecked desires passions
aversions and so on things you've been
acting out of so if you have developed
that attitude of of non giving into to
resistance to pain acceptance of
pleasure and then acting out of it you
have basically gradually started
removing things so you can't just
directly go head-on and extinguish the
fire but you can start removing that
which fire can take up as fuel and
eventually it will have to burn out
and it will burn out having not taking
anything new as fuel and that's when the
fire is extinguished and that's where
the literally there's nothing else then
to do so the sight sound smell stays
touches the eye decides the nose the
smells and so on the mind the thoughts
remain and would have said they those
things remain into target as well and
the beautiful recognizing beautiful
things recognizing ugly things all that
the target is still have you haven't
lost preferences nor anything like that
what the target that doesn't have is the
desire and lust in regard to his own
thought in the after his perceptions in
regard to his sights and smells tastes
touches and so on so by by practicing by
discerning the danger in these things
you would prevent yourself from
habitually choosing passion choosing a
version choosing Damas giving in
cultivating dwelling in it you would
prevent yourself from doing it by
preventing yourself from doing it you
are removing the basis for fire to to
keep finding fuel so indirectly speaking
then you are extinguishing the fire
which is kind of in a way a direct way
of doing it
removing the next thing the fire will
take up you know it will directly cause
that fire to burn out
stop disappear so that's why it's
important to recognize here under the
fire is on the basis of your attitude of
passion anger and darkness ill-will
aversion and down this it's not in the
eye in the sight in the consciousness
and so on
so the same goes the suit the coil
carries on for all the other senses
including the mind so the mind is on
fire phenomenon fire mind consciousness
is on fire nine impression is on fire
that which mind impression causes to
appear felt pleasant or painful neither
pleasure nor ninety painful the pleasant
that is also in fire on fire we walked
on fire with passion with anger with
darkness with birth aging death sorrow
lamentation pain grief in despair
so this carries on base is just piling
up that's what it is so it's on fire
with passion with anger with down this
because you delighting it you don't see
danger in it which then means you on
account of that fire it's on fire with
birth aging and death means birth aging
death all these things that are
affecting sight sound smell stage
touches mind and so on now they pertain
to you now they are exhibiting pressure
on you you are liable to them you are
subject to them because of accepting
things that that that that I born there
aging that are dying the body the senses
and so on another layer denim piling up
this sort of lamentation pink leaves
episode that means any sorrow any
lamentation any pain any grief any
despair on account of anything in this
life it's not specific any sorrow
lamentation pain grief and despair is
because you make yourself liable to it
because you you make yourself because
you cultivate passion anger and darkness
in regard to completely unrelated things
so you might be passionate about one
thing and then suffer on account of
something completely seemingly unrelated
it's because there is passion present in
experience you're liable to suffering on
account of anything so that's why it's
hard to approve these things and it
takes that constant repetition because
you cannot see a direct connection if
you could immediately see things your
passion about how the pain can resolve
there right away written immediately it
will be easy to restrain yourself but
that connection is covered up so
just rejoicing in a beautiful sight of a
familiar person or a person in love or
something like that oh why is that bad
well in itself it's not bad but having
an underlying attitude of passion
towards that feeling you experience on
account of that sight there's I mean the
the those impressions whatever they
caused to appeared it's felt pleasant
unpleasant or neutral you delight in
that your passion towards that feeling
you have anger towards the unpleasant
feeling or darkness to this neutral
feeling that's why because the passion
is present or anger or dullness you are
then liable to any type of suffering
when things change so as the Buddha
would say being you know being United
with things you don't want and separate
different things to what you want in
brief the five aggregates of your
experience like you experience the whole
being affected by assumption assuming
yes assuming no assuming neither yes nor
no giving into those attitudes no being
mindful about them and and basically
cultivating passion aversion and
darkness in regard to them that's what
you are liable to sorrow lamentation
pain grief and despair
absolutely regardless of specific things
that might cause them I trigger let's
say like that those those unpleasant
states so that's why the ultimate
understanding of the Four Noble Truths
is that suffering is determined by
craving not by anything else
so presence of craving inner experience
which is manifested through passion
manifested through anger manifested
through version presence of craving
means presence of suffering so it's like
the two sides of the same coin craving
is one side suffering is the other side
it's not a separate coin it's not
craving another's first and then
suffering follows presence of craving
means presence of suffering even if you
don't see it because you're looking on
this coin side of craving that's why you
get to know that suffering is there the
liability to suffering which is
suffering in itself is there because of
craving not because you've seen
something disagreeable and so on
so craving equal suffering craving means
suffering and then you could also say in
the in relation to disorder craving
means fire so if you have the attitude
of craving on account of feeling that's
impressed upon you you have the attitude
of either passion either anger or either
darkness three modes through which
craving manifest itself
oh and perpetuates itself so because of
craving you are then sorrowing lamenting
in pain in grieving sooner or later you
remove craving you cannot sorrow lump a
note be a grieving you'll be desperate
and I kind of anything even if it's the
worst possible misfortune comes your way
because those things cannot be the
reason for the presence of suffering
those things can then just be taken up
by a fire by passion by suffering but
it's suffering is not in there hmm so
that's what the bottom means here
furthermore in that suta they're seeing
those monks well a noble disciple means
at least a sotapanna means one who is
develop drive you that are craving means
suffering not the sights that I've seen
that's unpleasant craving means
suffering and not the sites that I've
seen the cause passion in me and so on
so for Noble Truths it's basically one
insight which means presence of craving
equals presence of suffering absence of
craving absence of suffering even if the
absence of suffering even if the
circumstances haven't changed if it's
all the same the only thing that changes
is absence of craving means you will not
suffer even if it's the circumstances
they use to make you suffer so having
understood that you then become weary of
the I weary of the forms in our
consciousness so weary of the domain of
sight any impression the sides can have
on you you realize well anything of see
hear smell taste touch heed exercises
pressure on me which if I am NOT mindful
off let's say like that means I will
give in to craving
I'm basically carelessly so that's why I
better not cultivate that careless
attitude towards the eye forms
eye-consciousness an eye impression so
being wary of the eye wary of the forms
not because I in forms are to blame but
because well basically you're an addict
of passion addict of aversion addict of
darkness so yeah that addiction is in
you but in order to start uprooting it
you need to be wary of those things that
you go for and in this case it's decides
in general not this like in the
beginning here you restrain this side on
account of that side but eventually with
your reflection and contemplation and
meditation you are avid any sight means
any pressure means any possibility of
craving so you want to be wary of it and
in other words you want to stop
welcoming it stop delighting in it stop
looking forward to the prospect of clay
please inside stop looking forward to
the prospect of avoiding the displeasing
signs so that's what it means you become
wary of the eye the phone with the eye
consciousness and anything of those things anyway
and anything of those things anyway
those things can impress you so that's
what Evers felt on account of it
Pleasant painful
neither Pleasant neither painful nor
Pleasant you become weary off so weary
of whatever you're currently feeling
weary of whatever you're currently
feeling so if you are say weary of the
present enduring feeling of pleasure
let's say so pleasure is there you're
not trying to deny try to get rid you
weary of it would you be able to blindly
carelessly just crave for it and act out
of the craving and give into desire and
lose your sense restraint impossible
so to being wary of the eye the forms
the experience of the sight of the eye
consciousness the pressure that's felt
on account of it oh now you're worried
of how you feel on account which which
means you automatically wary of all
these things and we're being wary of it
you will not give in to craving by not
giving in to craving you cannot then
perpetuate passion aversion
and darkness and without those things
fire cannot spread spread itself it runs
out of fuel so whether you're weary of
the sight sound smell stays touches the
point is to bring you back to be weary
of whatever its present enduring on the
level of the feeling whatever scarred in
the felt either Pleasant or if it's felt
unpleasantly or neither pleasantly nor
unpleasantly you're wary of that if
you're wary of that you cannot create
toward any of that feeling you cannot
lean towards Pleasant you cannot lean
away towards unpleasant feeling and you
cannot sort of lean into indolence and
darkness and account of neutral feeling
so simply by understanding where the
problem is which is what the right view
is you then get to exercise so to speak
these attitudes correctly so in the
pleasant feeling you get to exercise the
non leaning in the pleasant feeling in
the unpleasant feeling by being wary of
the unpleasant feeling you don't
automatically lean away from it so you
start exercising known or rather the
absence of leaning away from it and
that's what the Buddha meant in that in
the verse he says like oh if you if you
kind of fight the waves if you go if you
go against them you'll sink if you try
to go backwards it will it will so if
you find the ways you get tired if you
go backwards you get swept away and if
you try and stand still you you would
sink so how did you then cross to the
other Shore they are the Buddha he said
well across it by not fighting the waves
by not pulling backwards and by not
standing still so by not leaning towards
Pleasant feeling but not leaning away to
example as I'm feeling and by not being
sort of sinking in into darkness towards
neutral feeling that's how you will
remove the passion aversion and delusion
so the point there is that that you need
to so it's not like or will never lean
towards anything because you don't lean
towards anything you only lean on that
emotional level towards things that are
agreeable so then you don't lean towards things
so then you don't lean towards things
that are agreeable but then you should
Ben lien to us things that are
disagreeable because habitually you're
leaning away so simply by leaning back
towards the disagreeable you stop
leaning away now yeah okay you can then
double down and start leaning like
self-mortification but that's when you
don't have the context of to what extent
it's necessary that's why this applies
to the noble disciple now you know that
you lean only for the disappearance of
craving by the way craving means leaning
towards pleasure craving is there
leaning away from pain craving is there
so when you're leaning towards pleasure
lean away sufficiently enough for
craving to disappear that's it if you
don't have that as a criteria the
disappearance of craving is the measure
where you stop leaning away from
pleasure you then lean away too much and
that's the the simile we mentioned and
often that the dear to the simile of
bait suta in magic art which is when the
deer herd realizes all this displeasure
sense pleasures are basically a trap
they are a bait so then they shine it
they lean away not just from the bait
but they lean away from anything
agreeable anything there's anything that
comes from the domain where the bait is
which is why then they starve then the
other one is sort of completely careless
about it one is sort of denying it too
much so that's what I'm describing here
it's the attitude of
habitually just having an experience of
pleasant feeling you're leaning towards
it and you will lean towards it if
you're not wary of that feeling so
becoming weary of the feeling you stop
leaning towards it a bit chilly
sometimes you might lean away from it to
compensate for the amount you were
leaning forward and then same in the
unpleasant feeling you habitually in a
way which means sometimes you might need
to lean forward just to regain the
perspective on that unpleasant feeling
and counter their habitual leaning away
so you don't use it as a rule of thumb
that I will always lean away from from
Pleasant feeling there's no reason to
lean away from pleasant feeling if you
haven't been leaning towards because
sometimes you don't lean towards
pleasure even when you see it
but if if you just take it as a rule of
thumb that you will always lean away
from pleasure and always lean towards
pain to counter your craving means
you're doing it blindly it will only
correspond rightly sometimes and you're
not developing wisdom on account of it
that's when people basically start
blaming sight sound smell taste touches
for things they feel and for the craving
on account of it so then they simply
think that if they avoid certain sights
and smells tastes touches they're
avoiding the craving but you know you
might still well be leaning towards that
internally welcoming the lighting
accepting assuming that attitude so
that's why that the middle way is is
recognizing where the problem is of
craving and then that will determine
whether you lean towards or lean away
from it I mean if you are caught in in
constant denial of any pleasure even
pleasure you don't crave for you you're
overdoing the leaning away so you're not
having the middle ground
you're not seeing where the craving is
because craving can only be manifested
and then middle ground so understanding
then the weariness of the sight sound
smell stage touches creates a basis for
you to discern where that craving is
where that base where the necessary
condition for passion aversion and
dullness Azure account to which there is
all this fire of your senses that are
there burning up and you would be wary
of the eye not simply by you know being
mindful of what you're seeing and what
you're hearing and so on and attending
to it and try not to lose focus no how
can that possibly result in you being
wary of it now you aware of it when you
start looking into its nature discerning
the nature of sight sounds masters
touches as we said before but these are
things that I'm subjected to um nothing
you could I'm not including in their
control they're literally base I'm
oppressed by them my side sounds smells
tastes touches I cannot stop seeing
smelling tasting hearing and touching
and thinking I cannot stop it
so why do I still act and hold the view
and attitude as if they're mine and in
my control when I when I absolutely no
say in them so you start thinking like
that and you have to keep repeating
those reflections and drilling them in
and clarifying them more and more and
more that's how this sermon takes place
and that's how you are developing the
attitude of weariness towards the eye
and forms nose and smells and so on and
by being weary you'll be unable to be
careless leaning toward carelessly
leaning away and so on but being weary
as a basis you're then we will be unable
to crave by not craving you'll be unable
to suffer even if it's amidst the things
they used to cause yourself to suffer
and they says is that so being weary he
becomes dispassionate so being weary no
basis for craving no base for craving on
base for passion
so without passion you really get
understand so the fire does the smokes
gone because the fire stopped burning
and now see clearly what things are and
as they're as he says here he becomes he
becomes this passion this passionate
he's liberated so you're liberated from
that self-perpetuating fire and that you
kept providing unintentionally kept
providing fuel for so with liberation
you know that you are liberated and
that's the thing we moot as men we
Mouton et with liberation it is
liberated jnana hota the knowledge
manifests and that's important to know
so it's not like the liberation will
happen to you you had this special
magical experience where all the fire
disappeared and everything is ceased and
now you're just enlightened no no no you
know exactly the liberation came in a
kind of this passion that came in a kind
of non craving they came on account of
you discerning and drilling and training
yourself in becoming weary of the sight
sound smell taste touches for
which sense restraint was necessary
beforehand so when you are liberated you
know you are liberated the knowledge is
recognized ah I am free that's the other
hundred so not just that you are free
from these things you know what freedom
is it is with liberation it is liberated
he knows he understands
in other words Aaron knows that he knows
and knows how he knows as well so I'm
just emphasizing that because again
doesn't it's deeply rooted obviously in
order to kind of expect or if I just go
through these motions and then this
passion will occur and then
enlightenment will happen and I'm fixed
now it's simply work and the repetitive
training drilling and enduring patience
endurance sense restraint and just
reflection reflection if meditation
becomes then more composed form of the
same reflection thinking and pondering
what is thinking and pondering then in
first jhana other than reflection that
is now fully we drawn from any slightest
basis of passion in regard to the sense
sense pleasures so weariness will be
developed on account of correct
reflection and correct reflection will
be developed an account of correct
instruction and correct instruction will
be developed an account of well
correctly attending to what you hear
that also happens to be right so it's
it's two factors you need to find the
right instructions and you also need to
attend to it correctly because you might
have been hearing the right instructions
and disagreeing with it or dismissing it
or not accepting it because you haven't
be attending it rightly and the first
step of the right attention is to
recognize your own position do I know
for myself what craving is and we wanna
counter which I'm unable to suffer like
a noble disciple and why not huh no
which means I mustn't dismiss any
instruction that I come across simply
because of how it makes me feel the only
time I should dismiss is after I have
invested two fishermen or effort where I
understood that it's wrong and why it is
wrong often you would see that an attitude in
often you would see that an attitude in
yourself as well you come across
something and you just oh no this is
wrong okay so you had that attitude you
know denying it but now look at it and
ask yourself do I know why is this wrong
is it simply because this pleases me or
they actually see a contradiction in it
there is a flaw in it oh yes there is a
flaw okay so what is the flaw clarify it
explain it to yourself and if you
understand it able to explain if you
know that you know that there is a flaw
then fine
move on to the next instruction but more
often than not what people do is you
kind of go along pick up these views
bump from one instruction to the other
pick up bits and pieces never really
thinking about will get him getting to
the meaning of any of those you're just
accumulating the pile and then he has
some sort of a shape of a view and now
when you come across something that's
very much perceived as against the view
you simply rejected because it
displeases you it counters you or so it
feels not because you understood it is
wrong and to what extent it was wrong
and that's the most perilous so because
of that attitude of simply judging what
instructions you will heed and effort
you make because you don't look for the
meaning behind the instruction even the
one that pleases you you will not be
able to then develop that right
reflection without a rival fraction you
will not become weary or weary of things
because you're not really discerning the
the nature you need to discern by not
becoming weary you will not become
dispassionate and of being dispassionate
you will not be liberated by not being
liberated you will not be able to say oh
I'm liberated so that's for me it comes
down to well see even if you're not sort
of honor because this is wizardry first
so the mana it's still the same
principle how I might feeling am i
resisting my feeling am I rejecting
these instructions that are upsetting me
am I really
refusing to hear them because they're
displeasing me or is because no I've
genuinely understood it's wrong for this
reason this
in this reason but if you did understand
then you wouldn't be upset see if you
understand fool as a fool you cannot be
upset with a fool the only time you're
upset with fool is when he gets to you
and he gets to you when you don't
understand why that happened
so with if you come across an
instruction do you reject then you say
it's wrong make sure you do it because
you understood that it's wrong not
because it displeased you oh this is all
nonsense okay well please explain
nonsense means it's it's contradictory
it's nonsensical explain it why we're to
our extent if you are able to see that
clearly thence fine then you can reject
that and there will be no room for
passion because as we explained reading
the suitor passion is a result of you
craving so if you're passionately
rejecting this view means your passion
will basically under underneath that
you're craving against the displeasure
of that view that's where your argument
is rooted in that's where your attitude
is rooted and that's a very dangerous
place to be in because you could well be
rejecting the clearest purest
instruction that you could otherwise
understand and become an our hunch
yourself so I'm not saying you must then
exit well I mean it's clear what I'm
saying but I just want to repeat it
again so it's not about I mustn't reject
and I must accept every instruction
because I don't know which one's right
no you must use your discernment your
reflection and make sure you're not
rooted in simply how it made you feel so
you need to get to the bottom it you
need to understand the meaning of that
instruction if it's wrong you need to
see why it's wrong and then you can move
on then you will not just be acting out
of your feeling which will then which is
then preventing you from getting to
understand the nature of acting out of
your feeling which is what craving is so
then this sort of ends up by saying that
the monks they were there they were
pleased with blessed ones were they
delighted in them positively
and while this explanation was being
given those thousand monks through non
assuming the mind liberated became
liberated from art flows so that's
exactly points that through non craving
non passion they stopped assuming the
five agrees it stopped assuming control
of the final gates they stopped taking
them up is mine they stopped putting
themselves first so the new padana has
been completely dispelled in regard to
the final grades on account of removing
the craving and how you're feeling right
here right now now these monks they were
listening this and became around they
were obviously noble disciples of
various degrees because not just that
immediately made sense with this the
context that was resulting on a kind of
making sense of what the Buddha was
describing was sufficient for their
minds to be become fully established
upon that knowledge of liberation
through this passion through becoming
well through being weary of these things
the reason wise emphasize that now is
because just reading the last bed it can
you might just assume oh they just heard
a Buddha and boom era Han ship happened
no they've done all the work that the
Buddha said here in his few sentences
they tended beforehand so when they were
here listening to the bullet they just
got reminded of the context of non
craving non leaning towards non leaning
away he just got hammered in to the
point of oh yeah the holy life has been
laid down what should be done
I don't lean towards pleasure I don't
lean towards pain
I don't lean towards towards the I don't
lean into darkness and that's why then
they were our hands you